[
<speech as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" by="#CatherineMartin"
    eId="spk_2">
    <from>Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime
            time="2023-02-08T13:30:00+00:00" /></from>
    <p eId="para_13">Fáiltím roimh an deis labhairt leis an Roghchoiste um Thurasóireacht, Cultúr,
        Ealaíona, Spórt agus Meáin agus Meastacháin Athbhreithnithe 2023 dar luach €1.066 billiún
        san iomlán do Vóta 33 do Réimsí Clár A, B, D agus E á mbreithniú. Tá áthas orm sonraí a
        sholáthar maidir leis na bearta suntasacha chun tacú leis na hearnálacha a bhfuil mé
        freagrach astu agus chun iad a neartú, agus iad éascaithe ag an maoiniú seo. Táim an-sásta
        deis a fháil labhairt leis an gcoiste maidir le príomhthosaíochtaí mo Roinne agus an fhís a
        leagan amach do na hearnálacha luachmhara fairsinge seo. Cuireann na hearnálacha seo go mór
        le geilleagar na tíre, agus tacaíonn siad le folláine an duine aonair agus an phobail ar fud
        na hÉireann chomh maith.</p>
    <p eId="para_14"> Almost one year after pandemic restrictions ended, these sectors now face
        challenging economic conditions with high inflation and energy costs putting pressure on
        businesses. They must tackle the urgency of climate action so we can safeguard our planet
        for future generations. And of course they must play our part in Ireland’s response to the
        war in the Ukraine. As we have so often done in hard times, these sectors continue to
        reinforce our resilience, solidarity, and understanding; and support society’s cohesion and
        well-being.</p>
    <p eId="para_15"> Total funding for 2023 for the sectors supported by my Department is as
        follows. In relation to tourism: Funding for Fáilte Ireland for 2023 amounts to €94.7, this
        is to help drive the sustainability of our tourism sector, boost industry recruitment and
        retention and facilitate the establishment of a register of short-term letting properties;
        continued additional funding of €15 million for the tourism marketing fund, giving a total
        allocation of €63.2 million for overseas marketing of Ireland and the development of The
        Invitation project; Tourism Ireland funding of €20.8 million; €36.5 million for tourism
        product development; €4.5 million for Ireland-EU just transition tourism funding to support
        ambitious climate action through the promotion of sustainable tourism; and €7.75 million for
        the Brexit adjustment reserve fund to grow tourist numbers and associated revenues from
        Great Britain and Northern Ireland. The Minister of State will brief the committee in more
        detail on the position in respect of sport.</p>
    <p eId="para_16"> Prior to the onset of Covid-19, the tourism industry generated revenue of
        almost €6 billion supporting over 260,000 livelihoods equating to one in ten of all Irish
        jobs. Post pandemic, Irish tourism had a strong year in 2022,. Continued rebuilding lies
        ahead, however. Our primary focus now is on the sustainable development of this important
        economic and social sector, and marketing the island of Ireland as a desirable and
        competitive destination for both overseas visitors and domestic tourists.</p>
    <p eId="para_17"> We must remind ourselves that 2021 was an unprecedented year for arts and
        culture against the backdrop of the pandemic and the extensive restrictions that were still
        in place.</p>
    <p eId="para_18">Venues were closed or restricted to very limited audiences. Survival was the
        primary focus. Thankfully, this has all changed since early 2022. Against this backdrop
        significant levels of funding have been maintained with total funding for the arts and
        culture sector in 2023 amounting to €356.982 million.</p>
    <p eId="para_19"> The budget provides for: retention of the record €130 million funding for the
        Arts Council in recognition of the transformational impact of this funding and to support
        the sector; €35 million for the basic income for the arts pilot scheme, supporting 2,000
        artists and creative arts workers; funding of €30.2 million for cultural infrastructure and
        development including €7 million for artists’ spaces and climate adaptation measures, which
        will allow for progress in the ongoing programme of investment in our capital institutions
        including at the National Library of Ireland, the National Archives of Ireland and the
        Crawford Art Gallery; €11.5 million for the newly extended Creative Ireland programme,
        including a new shared island dimension; €6.6 million in funding for Culture Ireland for the
        promotion of Irish arts worldwide, an increase of €2 million on the 2022 allocation; €72.1
        million for the national cultural institutions to ensure the continuation of their
        high-quality services to the public; additional funding of €1 million for Screen Ireland
        giving a total record allocation of €37.9 million for the continued implementation of the
        Government’s ten-year audiovisual action plan.</p>
    <p eId="para_20"> I should mention the wonderful success of Irish film at the Oscars this year,
        with a record number of nominations for "The Banshees of Inisherin" and with "An Cailín
        Ciúin" making history for the Irish language on screen. This is a testament to the levels of
        investment, support and continued development of the screen industry in Ireland.</p>
    <p eId="para_21"> The budget also provides: a €3 million allocation towards the cost of
        developing a new archive and exhibition space as part of the overall national centre for
        research and remembrance; and €500,000 for supports for artists and arts workers as part of
        the Safe to Create programme, co-ordinated by Irish Theatre Institute, in collaboration with
        Minding Creative Minds.</p>
    <p eId="para_22"> Funding for the media and broadcasting sector in 2023 will total €306.64
        million and represents an innovative package which supports the sector from grassroots
        community radio and local newspapers to audiovisual media services and online regulation.
        The budget provides in particular for €7.8 million for the establishment of coimisiún na
        meán, the media commission, which will oversee effective regulation of online safety,
        support the provision of high-quality public service broadcasting, and put in place an
        expanded development and support framework for the wider media sector. I recently announced
        the appointment of new commissioners, including the Online Safety Commissioner, and they
        will take up their positions on an administrative basis next week. I intend to commence key
        provisions of the Online Safety and Media Regulation Act and formally establish an coimisiún
        next month.</p>
    <p eId="para_23"> An increased allocation of €7.3 million to TG4, will enable the launch of a
        new dedicated children’s channel, Cúla4, in September. This will be a totally new channel,
        operating from morning until the evening. It will include a children’s news service,
        entertainment and education content, drama and Irish animation. It will reflect the diverse
        backgrounds of children living in all parts of Ireland, but particularly in Gaeltacht and
        Irish-speaking communities. Its development will also support new jobs through the
        commissioning of additional content.</p>
    <p eId="para_24"> A total of €6 million has been allocated to establish a local democracy
        reporting scheme and a courts reporting scheme which will support local, regional and
        national media on a platform-neutral basis. These schemes will be the first of six new
        schemes recommended by the Future of Media Commission. Separately the technical group
        examining television licence reform will deliver its recommendations to me next month. That
        report will be brought to Government in due course.</p>
    <p eId="para_25"> Gabhaim buíochas le mo chomhghleacaithe Rialtais as a dtiomantas leanúnach do
        na hearnálacha a ndéanann mo Roinn ionadaíocht orthu, ar chodanna ríthábhachtacha dár
        ngeilleagar iad. Go deimhin, tá ár bhféiniúlacht, comhtháthú sóisialta, agus folláine
        fhisiciúil agus mheabhrach bunaithe ar na hearnálacha seo.</p>
    <p eId="para_26"> The Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, will address measures in the area for
        sport for 2023. I officially congratulate him on his appointment and I am looking forward to
        working with him.</p>
</speech>,
<speech as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" by="#CatherineMartin"
    eId="spk_6">
    <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2023-02-08T13:40:00+00:00" /></from>
    <p eId="para_35">It should be noted that budget 2022 was cast in a time when the impact of the
        Covid-19 pandemic on the sectors my Department supports was still all-encompassing. The 2022
        budget contained funding aimed at supporting those sectors through the worst of the pandemic
        when many of them were in complete shutdown. The total allocation for 2022 was €1.276
        billion, with €1.074 billion in current expenditure and €202 million in capital expenditure.
        Of the €1.074 billion in current funding, €290 million was provided on a once-off basis for
        Covid-support measures for initiatives including supports for live entertainment, sport and
        business-continuity funding in the tourism sector.</p>
    <p eId="para_36">This was all aimed at ensuring these sectors were sustained through the
        pandemic and would then emerge in a healthy position. The scale of that intervention in 2022
        was hugely significant for the sectors. My Department’s demonstrated support underlines the
        commitment of the Government to supporting these sectors and how much we valued these
        sectors through the pandemic.</p>
    <p eId="para_37"> As we emerged from the pandemic, in budget 2023, thankfully, there was no
        longer a need for the scale of intervention in respect of Covid-19 that was required in 2022
        because the restrictions had been lifted. However, the sectors supported by my Department
        are not completely recovered from the impact of the pandemic and therefore there is an
        ongoing need to support the sectors as they seek to fully recover. Accordingly, the 2023
        budget for my Department contains some once-off funding of approximately €98 million, not as
        much as was required in 2022 for the reasons I have outlined, but still quite a significant
        amount. Hence, there is an overall fall in the total budget for 2023 compared with 2022
        caused by the reduction in overall once-off funding of €121 million. Overall, the reduction
        year on year on the face of the budget is due mainly to the reduction in once-off funding
        from €219 million to €98 million.</p>
</speech>,
<speech as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" by="#CatherineMartin"
    eId="spk_8">
    <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2023-02-08T13:50:00+00:00" /></from>
    <p eId="para_39">I would point out that even though it has reduced from 2022 to 2023, before I
        was Minister the Revised Estimate, REV, gross total for the Department was €802 million,
        whereas even given the reduction in the last 12 months, the 2023 gross Revised Estimate is
        €1.166 billion, so it is still a significant increase in the last three years of this
        Government.</p>
</speech>,
<speech as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" by="#CatherineMartin"
    eId="spk_10">
<from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2023-02-08T13:50:00+00:00" /></from>
<p eId="para_41">Some €15 million in additional funding has been secured for overseas marketing of
Ireland. The budget always contains an additional €15 million for a range of industry initiatives,
including investments in skills development and retention of €3 million, and a €2 million increase
in funding for domestic marketing to promote Ireland's tourism offering to Irish holidaymakers. I
have also secured additional long-term funding for the hosting of the American college football
classic every August out to 2026. This will provide a strong boost to the sector in 2023 and we
would expect 40,000 overseas visitors for this years Notre Dame versus Navy game. There is also
additional funding of €3 million to allow Fáilte Ireland to continue its work in the area of
sustainability. Of course, there are other allocations of €36.5 million for tourism product
development. We have the basic income for the arts and that €35 million is secured to support 2,000
artists in that pilot scheme. We have €30.2 million for culture infrastructure and development,
€11.5 million for the newly extended Creative Ireland programme, €7 million for artists’ spaces and
climate adaptation measures and, of course, €6.6 million in funding for Culture Ireland, which is an
increase of €2 million on the 2022 allocation. The list is quite extensive and